Philadelphia, Pa. First Christian Church records, 1835-1974.
Congregational Library & Archives
Philadelphia, Pa. First Christian Church records, 1835-1974.
RG5488
Congregational Library & Archives
1.09 Cubic Feet
(1 box, 1 oversize folder)
The First Church of the Disciples of Christ in Philadelphia was chartered in 1841. In 1912, Irving S. Chenoweth became the past of the First Christian Church and under his leadership a new church building was constructed in 1917. The church joined with the United Church of Christ after 1957. This collection contains membership and administrative records and includes meeting minutes, newsletters, and vital membership records.
First Christian Church (Philadelphia, Pa.)
First Church of Disciples (Philadelphia, Pa.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Evangelival & Reformed Library & Archives in January 2024; 2024-01.
Historical Note
The First Church of the Disciples of Christ in Philadelphia was chartered in 1841, though the church's membership roll dates back to 1835. By the twentieth century, the church was more commonly called the First Christian Church. The church was located at the intersection of Berks and Marvine Streets. The church was evidently struggling in 1912 when Irving S. Chenoweth became pastor. Chenoweth was born in 1883 and graduated from the Union Theological Seminary in 1911. Under Chenowith's leadership, the struggling church changed locations to one at the intersections of Tenth Street and Boulevard. First services at the new location were held on May 21, 1917. At some point after 1957, the church joined the United Church of Christ. It is unclear if the church continues to exist today in some form or fashion.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains membership and administrative records for the First Christian Church in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The collection includes baptismal records, membership records, marriage records, records of deaths, church and board meeting minutes, newsletters, ladies aid society records, and an 1841 charter for the church.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into chronological order, by start date, with like and continuous materials grouped together.
Baptismal records.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Newsletters.; Chenoweth, Irving S.; First Christian Church (Philadelphia, Pa.); First Church of Disciples (Philadelphia, Pa.); Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Church history
- Membership records, 1835 1938; 1835-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- First Church of Disciples charter, 1841 (Folder 6)
- Church records, 1867 1885; 1867-1885 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Church records, 1892 1912; 1892-1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Ladies aid society minutes, 1904 1923; 1904-1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Church records, 1911 1920; 1911-1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Board records and minutes, 1920 1923; 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Board records and minutes, 1939 1942; 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Board records and minutes, 1943 1956; 1943-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Board records and minutes, 1954 1974; 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Newsletters, 1921 1922; 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Newsletters, 1922 1923; 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Newsletters, 1923 1924; 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Newsletters, 1924 1926; 1924-1926 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Newsletters, 1926 1928; 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Newsletters, 1928 1929; 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Newsletters, 1929 1930; 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Historic Memoir: Irving S. Chenoweth and the First Christian Church of Philadelphia, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Baptismal records, 1938 1965; 1938-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cradle roll, 1943 1967; 1943-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Church meeting minutes, 1943 1974; 1943-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Membership records, 1954 1968; 1954-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)